Robert Wilson Shufeldt Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Robert Wilson Shufeldt Papers 1836-1910 (bulk 1860-1880)
MSS52688
Shufeldt, Robert Wilson, 1822-1895
15,000 items
37 containers
15 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Naval officer, explorer, and diplomat. Correspondence, journals, diaries, notebooks, logbooks, subject files, newspaper clippings, and printed matter relating to Shufeldt’s career in the navy and as an explorer and diplomat.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Atkinson, Edward, 1827-1905--Correspondence.; Bache, A. D. (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867--Correspondence.; Bancroft, George, 1800-1891--Correspondence.; Bell, Henry Haywood, 1808-1868--Correspondence.; Boggs, Charles Stuart, 1811-1888--Correspondence.; Bradford, William, 1823-1892--Correspondence.; Butler, Benjamin F. (Benjamin Franklin), 1795-1858--Correspondence.; Carpenter, Cyrus Clay, 1829-1898--Correspondence.; Dahlgren, John Adolphus Bernard, 1809-1870--Correspondence.; Du Pont, Samuel Francis, 1803-1865--Correspondence.; Farragut, David Glasgow, 1801-1870--Correspondence.; Fish, Hamilton, 1808-1893--Correspondence.; Hargous, P. A. (Peter A.)--Correspondence.; Henshaw, David, 1791-1852--Correspondence.; Hopkins, Alfred--Correspondence.; Jenkins, Thornton A. (Thornton Alexander), 1811-1893--Correspondence.; Kennedy, John Pendleton, 1795-1870--Correspondence.; Kondō, Masuki--Correspondence.; Li, Hongzhang, 1823-1901--Correspondence.; Mackenzie, Alexander Slidell, 1803-1848--Correspondence.; Mason, J. M. (James Murray), 1798-1871--Correspondence.; Perry, Matthew Calbraith, 1794-1858--Correspondence.; Porter, David D. (David Dixon), 1813-1891--Correspondence.; Seward, William H. (William Henry), 1801-1872--Correspondence.; Shufeldt family--Correspondence.; Shufeldt, Mason A. (Mason Abercrombie), 1852-1892. Mason A. Shufeldt papers. 1883-1893.; Shufeldt, Robert Wilson, 1822-1895.; Smith, Truman, 1791-1884--Correspondence.; Stevens, Benjamin Franklin, 1833-1902--Correspondence.; Walker, John Grimes, 1835-1907--Correspondence.; Welles, Gideon, 1802-1878--Correspondence.
Organizations
Ticonderoga (Sloop of war); United States. Navy--History--19th century.
Subjects
Diplomatic and consular service, American--Cuba.; Voyages around the world.
Places
Africa--Discovery and exploration.; Africa--Foreign relations--United States.; Asia--Foreign relations--United States.; Cuba--Foreign relations--United States.; Mexico--Discovery and exploration.; Tehuantepec, Isthmus of (Mexico)--Surveys.; United States--Foreign relations--1861-1865.; United States--Foreign relations--19th century.; United States--Foreign relations--Africa.; United States--Foreign relations--Asia.; United States--Foreign relations--Cuba.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Naval operations.
Occupations
Diplomats.; Explorers.; Naval officers.
Provenance
The papers of Robert Wilson Shufeldt, naval officer, explorer, and diplomat, were deposited in the Library of Congress by the Naval Historical Foundation in 1949, 1952, and 1954, and converted to a gift in 1998.
Additional Guides
In 1969 the Library published Robert Wilson Shufeldt, a Register of His Papers in the Library of Congress.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Robert Wilson Shufeldt are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1822, Feb. 21 Born, Red Hook, N.Y.
1839 Appointed midshipman in the U.S. Navy
1839 1840 Duty in USS United States, Home Squadron
1840 1841 Duty in USS Potomac, Brazil Squadron
1841 1842 Duty in USS Marion, Brazil Squadron
1842 1843 Duty in USS Bainbridge, Home Squadron
1843 1844 Duty in USS Potomac, Home Squadron
1844 1845 Duty at the Naval School, Philadelphia, Pa.
1845 Promoted to passed midshipman
1845 1846 Coast survey duty
1846 Duty in USS United States, Africa Squadron
1846 1848 Duty in USS Marion, Africa and Mediterranean Squadrons
1847 Married Sarah Hutchins Abercrombie (died 1871)
1849 Duty in USS Morris
1850 1851 Duty in USS Atlantic
1851 Duty in USS Georgia
1851 1854 On leave from the navy
1854 Commissioned lieutenant Resigned from the navy
1854 1856 Chief officer, Collins Steamship Line
1856 1861 Commanded commercial ships and helped survey the Isthmus of Tehuantepec (Mexico)
1861 1863 Consul general, Havana, Cuba 1862 Served on a mission to Mexico
1863 Commissioned commander Commanded USS Conemaugh, South Atlantic Blockade Squadron
1863 1865 Commanded USS Proteus, East Gulf Squadron
1865 1866 Commanded USS Hartford, East India Squadron
1866 1868 Commanded USS Wachusett, East India-Asiatic Squadron
1868 Ordnance duty, New York Navy Yard
1868 1869 Commanded New York Naval Rendezvous
1869 1870 Commanded USS Minantonomoh
1870 Promoted to captain Ordnance duty, Portsmouth Navy Yard
1870 1871 Commanded Tehuantepec (Mexico) Survey Expedition
1871 1872 Commanded USS Wabash, European Squadron
1872 1873 Commanded USS Plymouth, European Squadron
1873 1875 Executive officer, New York Navy Yard
1875 1878 Chief of the Bureau of Equipment and Recruiting
1878 1880 Commanded USS Ticonderoga on a world cruise sponsored by the Department of the Navy and Department of State
1881 Naval attaché, Peking, China
1882 1884 President, Naval Advisory Board
1883 1884 Superintendent, Naval Observatory, Washington, D.C
1884 Promoted to rear admiral Retired from the navy
1889 Declined post of U.S. minister to China
1895, Nov. 6 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Robert W. Shufeldt (1822-1895) span the years 1836-1910, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1860-1880. Shufeldt’s forty-five year naval career was interrupted by a nine-year period in the merchant marine service and in surveying for a proposed isthmian canal route. The correspondence for his broken-service years, however, includes many papers of interest on naval affairs.
The Shufeldt collection consists primarily of correspondence, letterbooks, and subject files, supplemented by diaries, notebooks, journals, logbooks, newspaper clippings, printed matter, and a small file of material concerning explorations in Africa by Shufeldt’s youngest son, Mason. The topics of interest are the nineteenth-century navy, its growth and development; Civil War naval and diplomatic activities; foreign relations in the 1870s and 1880s, especially with Africa and Asia; and the Tehuantepec, Mexico, surveying expeditions. The collection is organized into nine series: Diaries, Notebooks, Logbooks, and Journals; Letterbooks, Letterpress Books, and Letter Index Books; Official Correspondence; General Correspondence; Subject File; Newspaper Clippings; Printed Matter; Miscellany; and Mason A. Shufeldt File.
Shufeldt resigned his commission in the navy in 1854 and entered the merchant marine to command the Quaker City. Later, he became interested in the construction of a canal across the Isthmus of Tehuantepec in Mexico and in 1860 led an expedition through that region. In 1861, Shufeldt was appointed consul general to serve in Cuba. Correspondents for the years 1839-1861 include A. D. Bach, George Bancroft, Charles Stuart Boggs, Benjamin F. Butler, John Adolphus Dahlgren, Samuel Ffrancis Du Pont, David Glasgow Farragut, John Pendleton Kennedy, James Murray Mason, Matthew Calbraith Perry, David D. Porter, and Gideon Welles.
Shufeldt returned to active duty in the navy in 1863 with the rank of commander. During the Civil War, her served both ashore and afloat. After the Civil War, Shufeldt served at sea in the Far East and in 1868 he returned to the United States and was assigned ordnance duty ashore in New York.
In 1870, Shufeldt was promoted to the rank of captain and was assigned special duty in command of a survey expedition to Tehuantepec, Mexico. After the exploration, Shufeldt recommended that this territory be considered as a likely site for a transisthmus canal.
In 1878, Shufeldt was given command of the Ticonderoga that was to sail on a round-the-world cruise. The documentation for the cruise fills about one-third of the containers in this collection. After returning to the United States in 1881, he was reassigned to Peking, China, as the naval attaché.
Shufeldt was appointed president of the Naval Advisory Board, for which he served two years before retiring in 1884. It was during this last tour of duty that he helped formulate the plans for a new navy incorporating the technological advance from sail to steam propulsion and from wood to iron and steel hulls.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in nine series:
Diaries, Notebooks, Logbooks, and Journals, 1865-1880
Letterbooks, Letterpress Books, and Letter Index Books, 1864-1880
Official Correspondence, 1839-1889
General Correspondence, 1838-1900
Subject File, 1861-1883
Newspaper Clippings, 1859-1899
Printed Matter, 1849-1910
Miscellany, 1836-1893
Mason A. Shufeldt File, 1883-1893
Container List
- Diaries, Notebooks, Logbooks, and Journals, 1865-1880 (Box 1-2)
  Diaries, notebooks, log abstracts, logbooks, navigational data, journals, and other writings.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Diary of Hartford, 1865, Aug. -Dec. (Box 1)
  - Notebook, Wachusett, 1866-1867 (Box 1)
  - Logbook, Wachusett (Box 1)
    - 1866, Sept.-1867, Mar. (Box 1)
    - 1867 (Box 1)
      - Mar.-June (Box 1)
      - June-Nov. (Box 1)
    - 1867, Nov.-1868, Jan. (Box 2)
  - Journal, Mayflower and Kansas, 1870, Nov.-1871, May (Box 2)
  - Diary (Box 2)
    - 1875 (Box 2)
    - 1876 (Box 2)
    - 1877 (Box 2)
    - 1878 (Box 2)
  - Journal of F. A. Miller, Ticonderoga (Box 2)
    - 1878, Dec.-1879, Aug. (Box 2)
    - 1879, Aug.-Dec. (Box 2)
    - 1879, Dec.-1880, May (Box 2)
- Letterbooks, Letterpress Books, and Letter Index Books, 1864-1880 (Box 3-4)
  Copies of correspondence and reports sent by Shufeldt as commander of various ships.
  A few of the volumes are indexed.
  - Letterbook (Box 3)
    - Proteus, 1864-1865 (Box 3)
    - Wachusett, 1866-1868 (Box 3)
  - Letter index book, Minantonomoh, 1869-1870 (Box 3)
  - Letterbook (Box 3)
    - Kansas, 1870, Oct. -Nov. and Mayflower, 1870, Nov.-1871, Mar. (Box 3)
    - Mayflower, 1871, Mar.-Aug. (Box 3)
  - Letter index book, Ticonderoga, 1878, Dec.-1880, Nov. (Box 3)
  - Letterpress book, Ticonderoga (Box 4)
    - 1878, Dec.-1880, Nov. (Box 4)
    - 1878, Dec.-1880, Nov. (Box 4)
    - 1879, Jan.-July (Box 4)
- Official Correspondence, 1839-1889 (Box 5-10)
  Letters received and a few drafts of letters sent.
  Arranged chronologically. Correspondence concerning Shufeldt’s years in Cuba, the Tehuantepec Survey Expedition, and the world cruise in the Ticonderoga is in the Subject File.
  - 1839-1862 (Box 5)
  - 1863-1865 (Box 6)
  - 1866 (Box 7)
  - 1867 (Box 8)
  - 1868-1872 (Box 9)
  - 1873-1889 (Box 10)
- General Correspondence, 1838-1900 (Box 11-17)
  Letters received and a few drafts of letters sent, mostly of a personal and family nature, but some material relating to Shufeldt’s activities in Cuba, Mexico, and elsewhere.
  - 1838-1861 (Box 11)
  - 1862-1867 (Box 12)
  - 1868-1870 (Box 13)
  - 1870-1871 (Box 14)
  - 1872-1875 (Box 15)
  - 1876-1884 (Box 16)
  - 1887-1900, undated (Box 17)
- Subject File, 1861-1883 (Box 18-29)
  Correspondence, reports, memoranda, manuscripts, maps, printed matter, newspaper clippings, drafts of writings, bills and receipts, and miscellaneous items pertaining to Cuba, the Tehuantepec Survey Expedition, and the Ticonderoga world cruise.
  Material concerning Cuba and Tehuantepec Survey Expedition is chronologically arranged and files concerning the Ticonderoga are arranged according to the area covered by the cruise.
  - Cuba, 1861-1863, undated (Box 18)
    - Correspondence (Box 18)
      - 1861, May-1862, Jan. (Box 18)
      - 1862, Feb.-1863, Apr., undated (Box 19)
    - Bills, receipts, and inventories (Box 19)
    - Miscellany (Box 19)
  - Tehuantepec Survey Expedition, Mexico, 1861-1873 (Box 20)
    - Correspondence (Box 20)
    - Bills, receipts, and inventories (Box 21)
    - Maps (Box 21)
    - Miscellany (Box 21)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 21)
    - Printed matter (Box 21)
  - World cruise, Ticonderoga, 1879-1883, undated (Box 22)
    - West Africa (Box 22)
    - Angola (Box 22)
    - South Africa (Box 22)
    - Congo (Box 22)
    - Dahomey (Box 22)
    - Sierra Leone (Box 22)
    - Zanzibar (Box 22)
    - Johanna (Box 22)
    - Madagascar (Box 22)
    - Aden (Box 22)
    - India (Box 22)
    - Singapore (Box 22)
    - Japan (Box 22)
    - Liberia (Box 23)
    - China (Box 24)
    - Korea (Box 24)
    - General correspondence (Box 25)
    - Maps (Box 25)
    - Oriental documents (Box 25)
    - Miscellany (Box 25)
    - Unpublished manuscript (Box 26)
      - Chapters 1-14 (Box 26)
      - Chapters 15-19 (Box 27)
    - Collected material for the manuscript (Box 27)
      - Liberia (Box 27)
      - South Africa (Box 27)
      - Middle East (Box 27)
      - India (Box 27)
      - Singapore (Box 28)
      - Philippine Islands (Box 28)
      - Japan (Box 28)
      - China (Box 28)
      - Korea (Box 28)
      - Miscellany (Box 29)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1859-1899 (Box 30-31)
  Clippings chiefly concerned with naval incidents.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - China (Box 30)
  - Gherardi, Bancroft-Walker, John, controversy (Box 30)
  - Japan (Box 30)
  - Interocean canal (Box 30)
  - Korea (Box 30)
  - Liberia (Box 31)
  - Miscellany (Box 31)
  - St. Helena (Box 31)
  - Sierra Leone (Box 31)
  - U.S. Navy (Box 31)
  - Quaker City (Box 31)
  - Ticonderoga (Box 31)
- Printed Matter, 1849-1910 (Box 32-33)
  Aticles, pamphlets, speeches, general orders, and other writings.
  - 1849-1910, undated (Box 32)
  - Minantonomoh, 1869-1870 (Box 33)
- Miscellany, 1836-1893 (Box 34-35)
  An account book, calling cards and invitations, notes and fragments, inventories, quartermaster reports, ship descriptions, officer register, ship specifications and blueprints, admiralty board arguments, bills, receipts, inventories, copies of treaties, certificates and awards, poetry, songs, and essays.
  Arranged by topic.
  - Account book, 1876-1877 (Box 34)
  - Calling cards and invitations, 1870-1882, undated (Box 34)
  - Notes and fragments, mostly undated (Box 34)
  - Poetry notes and fragments, mostly undated (Box 34)
  - Inventories, quartermaster reports, and ship descriptions, 1863-1870, undated (Box 34)
  - Officer registers and related material, 1864-1870, undated (Box 34)
  - Ship specifications and blueprints, including material by and about John Ericsson, 1864-1881, undated (Box 34)
  - Admiralty board arguments, undated (Box 34)
  - Bills, receipts, and inventories, 1862-1893, undated (Box 35)
  - Copies and treaties between the United States and foreign countries, 1836-1880 (Box 35)
  - Certificates, awards, and passports, 1853-1861 (Box 35)
  - Poems, songs, and essays written aboard Proteus and Hartford, 1864-1868 (Box 35)
- Mason A. Shufeldt File, 1883-1893 (Box 36-37)
  Correspondence, reports, writings, and miscellaneous material. This file is mostly concerned with Mason A. Shufeldt’s explorations of Africa.
  Arranged by topic and therein chronologically.
  - General correspondence (Box 36)
  - Madagascar expedition (Box 36)
    - Bills and receipts (Box 36)
    - Correspondence (Box 36)
    - Maps (Box 36)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 36)
    - Photographs (Box 36)
    - Printed matter (Box 37)
    - Reports (Box 37)
    - Writings (Box 37)
  - Columbian World Exposition, Chicago, Ill. (Box 37)
  - Miscellany (Box 37)